Guide to the Anson Phelps Stokes Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Journals, Speeches, Writings, and Research Materials, 1896-1954, (primarily 1896-1927, 1951-1954); PART II. II; 4 linear feet (10 boxes)
  - Books
    - A History of Universities
      - Chapter VI, typescript with notations (first draft?) (Box 69, Folder 933)
      - Chapter VI, typescript with notations (Box 69, Folder 934)
      - Chapter VII, typescript with notations (first draft?) (Box 69, Folder 935)
      - Chapter VII, typescript with notations (Box 69, Folder 936)
      - Chapter VIII, typescript with notations (first draft?) (Box 69, Folder 937)
      - Chapter VIII, typescript with notations (Box 69, Folder 938)
      - Chapter IX, typescript with notations (first draft?) (Box 69, Folder 939)
      - Chapter IX, typescript with notations (Box 69, Folder 940)
      - Chapter X, typescript with notations (first draft?) (Box 69, Folder 941)
      - Chapter X, typescript with notations (Box 69, Folder 942)
      - Chapter XI, manuscript (Box 69, Folder 943)
      - Chapter XI, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 944)
      - Chapter XII, manuscript (first draft?) (Box 70, Folder 945)
      - Chapter XII, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 946)
      - Chapter XII, manuscript (first draft?) (Box 70, Folder 947)
      - Chapter XII, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 948)
      - Chapter XIV, manuscript (first draft?) (Box 70, Folder 949)
      - Chapter XIV, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 950)
      - Chapter XV, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 951)
      - Chapters XVI and XVII, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 952)
      - Chapters XXIII and XIX, typescript with notations (Box 70, Folder 953)
      - Chapter XX, typescript with notations (Box 71, Folder 954)
      - Chapter XXI, transcript with notations (Box 71, Folder 955)
      - Chapters XXII and XXIII, typescript with notations (Box 71, Folder 956)
      - Chapter XXIV, typescript with notations (Box 71, Folder 957)
      - Chapters XXV and XXVIII typescript with notations (Box 71, Folder 958)
      - Chapter XXX and Appendices, typescript with notations (Box 71, Folder 959)
      - Descriptive Bibliography (Box 71, Folder 960)
      - A Bibliography of Books Wanted on University History (Box 71, Folder 961)
      - Notes for Later Chapters (Box 71, Folder 962)
      - Notes (Box 71, Folder 963)
      - Illustration note cards (Box 72, Folder 964)
    - Church and State in the United States
      - Chapter XII and notes for Chapter XX, typescript with notations (Box 72, Folder 965)
      - Notes for Chapters XXI, XXII and XXIII, typescript with notations (Box 72, Folder 966)
      - Part Eight, typescript with notations (Box 72, Folder 967)
      - Notes re: illustrations (Box 72, Folder 968)
      - Correspondence re: illustrations, 1942 January 16 - 1949 July 27, 1949 August 1 - 1950 January 19, undated (Box 72, Folder 969-970)
      - List of illustrations (Box 72, Folder 971)
      - Photographs and Illustrations (Box 72, Folder 972-977)
      - Materials for possible includion in the second edition (Box 72, Folder 978)
- Subject Files, 1911-1954, (primarily 1911-1929, 1951-1954); PART II. III; 6 linear feet (15 boxes)
  In Part II, Series III the material is grouped by subject: an institution, organization or project in which Stokes was involved. The eleven subjects in alphabetical order are:
  A. American Academy in Rome
  B. American University Union in Europe
  C. General Board of Religious Education
  D. General and International Education Boards
  E. Phelps Stokes Corporation
  F. Phelps Stokes Estates
  G. Phelps-Stokes Fund
  H. Russian Refugee Relief
  I. St. Paul's School
  J. Washington Cathedral
  K. Yale-in-China
  Within a subject, items may be filed in chronological order or arranged by type of material.
  NOTE: The Phelps Stokes Estates later bacame the Phelps Stokes Corporation and both groups of material deal with family properties and investments. The Phelps-Stokes Fund is completely separate and was established by the will of Caroline Phelps Stokes to support educational and housing projects in the United States and Africa.
  - American Academy in Rome
    - Correspondence, 1911 February - 1920 February (Box 73, Folder 979-984)
    - Minutes of the meetings of the Board of Trustees and Executive Committee, 1912 - 1919 (Box 73, Folder 985-987)
    - Annual report, 1914 February 10 - December 22 (Box 73, Folder 988)
    - Reports of the Directors in Rome, 1913 (Box 73, Folder 989)
    - Financial statements, 1913 - 1917 (Box 73, Folder 990)
    - Report of the committee of the School of Fine Arts, 1919 (Box 73, Folder 991)
    - Report of the Director of the School of Fine Arts, n.y.
    - Report of the Acting Director of the School of Classical Studies, 1915 September 30 (Box 73, Folder 992)
    - Proposed pension fund for the servants of the American Academy in Rome, undated
    - Abstract of an address by Jesse Benedict Carter, 1914 March 14
    - Newsletters, 1918 - 1919, (n.y.] (Box 73, Folder 993)
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 1920 (Box 74, Folder 994)
    - By-laws (Box 74, Folder 995)
    - Materials relating to AAR, 1907 - 1913, 1916 - 1918, undated (Box 74, Folder 996-997)
  - American University Union in Europe
    - American University Union in Europe, 1917 - 1918, 1922, undated (Box 74, Folder 998)
      See also: J. W. Cunliffe, Part I, Series I, box 1, folder 9 See also: Part I, Series I, Horatio S. Krans, Part I, box 29, folder 47 See also: George H. Nettleton, Part I, Series I, box 36, folder 593
  - General Board of Religious Education
    - Correspondence, 1913 November - 1914 November (Box 74, Folder 999)
    - Correspondence, 1915 February - 1919 Nov, undated (Box 74, Folder 1000-1002)
    - Minutes, abstracts and agendas, 1913 - 1919 (Box 74, Folder 1003-1004)
    - Financial statements, 1913 - 1917, undated (Box 74, Folder 1005)
    - General Secretary's monthly letters, 1915 (Box 74, Folder 1006)
    - Annual report, 1918 - 1919 (Box 74, Folder 1006)
    - Department of Parochial Education, 1913 December 10, 1914 February 4
    - Reports of committees, councils and individuals, 1915, 1917, undated (Box 75, Folder 1007)
    - Revision of the Canons of Ordination Additional miscellaneous items, 1919 (Box 75, Folder 1008)
    - Printed matter, 1912 - 1913, 1915 - 1916, 1919, undated, 1914 - 1917, undated (Box 75, Folder 1009-1010)
  - General and International Education Boards
    - Correspondence, [1903], 1910 September - 1914 January - October (Box 75, Folder 1011-1012)
    - Correspondence, 1915 January - 1918 March (Box 75, Folder 1013-1017)
    - Correspondence, 1918 May - 1923 March (Box 76, Folder 1018-1020)
    - Minutes of board meetings, 1912 - 1913 (Box 76, Folder 1021)
    - Minutes of board Meetings, 1915 - 1916 January (Box 76, Folder 1021 a)
    - Minutes of board Meetings, 1914, 1916 March - 1917 Jun, 1917 December 6, 1918 January - October (Box 76, Folder 1022-1028)
    - Minutes of board meetings, 1918 December - 1919 Sep, 1919 May - Jun, 1919 December - 1920, 1921 February - April (Box 77, Folder 1029-1035)
    - Dockets, 1912 - 1915 (Box 77, Folder 1036)
    - Exhibits, 1917 December 6, 1918 May 23 (Box 77, Folder 1037)
    - Docket, 1918 May 23
    - Docket and exhibits, 1918 December 5 (Box 77, Folder 1038)
    - Docket, 1919 February 27, 1919 May 22 (Box 78, Folder 1039-1040)
    - Exhibits, 1919 May 22 (Box 78, Folder 1041)
    - Docket, 1919 December 4 (Box 78, Folder 1042)
    - Docket and exhibits, 1920 February 26 - May 27 (Box 78, Folder 1043-1044)
    - Docket of special meeting at White Plains, 1920 November 4-6 (Box 78, Folder 1045)
    - Docket and exhibits, 1921 February 24 (Box 78, Folder 1046)
    - Docket, exhibits and supplementary docket, 1921 May 26 (Box 79, Folder 1047)
    - Exhibits, 1920 December 2, 1928 May 24 (Box 79, Folder 1048)
    - Financial reports, 1916 - 1921 (Box 79, Folder 1049-1053)
    - Financial statements, 1912 - 1916 (Box 79, Folder 1054-1058)
    - Report of the Secretary, 1914 - 1917 (Box 80, Folder 1059-1069)
    - Educational progress in Alabama, from the report of Professor Thomas, 1914 June - 1915 June (Box 80, Folder 1061)
    - A Report-on the Subject of a Modern School by Abraham Flexner (Box 80, Folder 1062)
    - Reports of J. L. Bond, State Agent, Rural Schools for Arkansas, 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1063)
    - Report of L. C. Brogden, State Agent, Rural Schools for North Carolina, 1914 November
    - Reports of F. C. Button, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools for Kentucky, 1913 - 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1064)
    - Reports of T. J. Coates, Agent, White Rural Schools for Kentucky, 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1065)
    - Reports of Jackson Davis, Supervisor, Rural Elementary Schools for Negroes in Virginia, 1912 - 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1066)
    - Reports of Leo M. Favrot, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools of Arkapsas, 1913 - 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1067)
    - Reports of George D. Goddard, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools of Georgia, 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1068)
    - Reports of J. B. Hobdy, State Agent, White Rural Schools for Alabama, 1914 - 1915 (Box 80, Folder 1069)
    - Summary of reports of J. B. Hobdy, State Agent for Rural Schools in Alabama, 1915 July 1 - 1916 January 1 (Box 80, Folder 1070)
    - Reports of N. C. Newbold, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools in North Carolina, 1913 - 1914 (Box 80, Folder 1071)
    - Reports of James L. Sibley, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools for Alabama, 1913 - 1915 (Box 81, Folder 1072)
    - Reports of James L. Sibley, State Supervisor of Negro Rural Schools for Alabama, 1915 - 1916 (Box 81, Folder 1073)
    - Reports of S. L. Smith, Agent, Negro Rural Schools for Tennessee, 1914 (Box 81, Folder 1074)
    - Report of W. H. Smith, State Agent, Rural Schools for Mississippi, 1914 September 30
    - Confidential memos of Abraham Flexner and Jerome D. Greene, 1914, 1919 (Box 81, Folder 1075)
    - Reports on Secondary school education in the southern United States, 1909?, 1912?, 1913?, undated (Box 81, Folder 1076)
    - Reports on secondary school education in the southern United States, 1908?, 1912?, 1915 (Box 81, Folder 1077)
    - Teacher training inssouthern state universities, undated (Box 81, Folder 1078)
    - "The Changes Needed in American Secondary Education" by Charles W. Eliot, undated (Box 81, Folder 1079)
    - "Shall Latin Continue to be Required of Candidates for the Degree of Bachelor of Arts?" by Charles W. Eliot, undated (Box 81, Folder 1080)
    - Proposal for Model and Demonstration Public School Systems for Certain Townships in New Hampshire" by Henry C. Morrison, undated (Box 81, Folder 1081)
    - "Report of a Study of Hampton Institute" by Paul H. Hanus, undated (Box 81, Folder 1082)
    - Survey of conditions in certain colleges and universities with reference to teachers salaries, 1920 April
    - "The Colleges and Rural Life" by Frederick T. Gates, Graduate School of Business Administration of Harvard University, undated (Box 81, Folder 1083)
    - Special Report of the County Training Schools for Colored Teachers in the State of Kentucky, undated
    - A Rural Organization Service, no date
    - Report on Veterinary Work in Europe" by Carl Tenbroeck, undated (Box 81, Folder 1084)
    - Report of Farmers' Cooperative Demonstration Work to the General Education Board, 1913 May (Box 81, Folder 1085)
    - Digest of Report of the Farm Demonstration Work in Maine for the Year, 1915 (Box 82, Folder 1086)
    - "The Farmers' Cooperative Demonstration Work' by J. A. Evans, undated
    - "Farm Demonstration in Maine" by G.A. Yeaton, undated
    - 'Agricultural Appropriation Bill... The Farmers' Cooperative Demonstration Work and the General Education Board'by John A. Small, 1914 June 25
    - Project: Marketing Farm Products, undated
    - College and University profiles, 1913, 1918, undated (Box 82, Folder 1087)
    - Materials relating to contributions made to: colleges and universities by the General Education Board, 1912 - 1914, 1918 - 1920, undated (Box 82, Folder 1088)
    - School, college and university bulletins (Box 82, Folder 1089)
    - Materials relating to the General Education Board and its. policies (Box 82, Folder 1090)
    - Press releases, 1916, n.y. (Box 82, Folder 1091)
    - By-laws, 1912 - 1921 (Box 82, Folder 1092-1093)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentified materials (Box 82, Folder 1094)
    - General Education Board
      See: Wallace Butterick, Part II, box 7, folder 104 See: Abraham Flexner, Part I, box 20, folder 323 See: Wickliffe Rose, Series I, Section A
  - Phelps Stokes Corporation
    - General manager's reports, 1931 December 8, 1933 October 10 (Box 82, Folder 1095)
    - Correspondence, 1951 - 1954 (Box 82, Folder 1096)
  - Phelps-Stokes Estates
    - Correspondence, 1914 - 1915 (Box 82, Folder 1097)
    - Correspondence, 1916 - 1921 (Box 82, Folder 1098)
    - Minutes of the meetings of directors and trustees, 1914, - 1916 (Box 82, Folder 1099-1100)
    - Minutes of the meetings of directors and trustees, 1917 - 1922 (Box 83, Folder 1101-1102)
    - President's reports, 1914, 1915, 1916, 1918, 1919, 1920 (Box 83, Folder 1103)
    - General manager's reports, 1914 January - 1916 November (Box 83, Folder 1104-1108)
    - General manager's reports, 1917-1919 June (Box 84, Folder 1109-1111)
    - General manager's reports, 1919 November - 1921 June (Box 84, Folder 1112-1113)
    - Additional legal and financial documents (Box 84, Folder 1114)
    - Materials relating to the Madison Square Hotel and Home of the Advertising Men's League (Box 84, Folder 1115)
  - Phelps-Stokes Fund
    - Correspondence, 1951 - 1955 (Box 85, Folder 1116-1117)
    - Minutes and reports, 1951 April - 1952 April, 1952 June - 1953 September (Box 85, Folder 1118-1119)
    - By-laws, notes and memoranda (Box 85, Folder 1120)
    - Phelps-Stokes Fund
      See: Francis Louis Slade, Part I, box 131 See: Thomas Jesse Jones, Part I, box 27, folder 434 See: Channing H. Tobias, Part I, box 126, folder 2261-2264 See: Ida A. Tourtellot, Series I, Section A
  - Russian Refugee Relief
    - Correspondence, memoranda and reports, [1920, 1922, 1926], 1927 August - 1928, undated, 1928 Jan, 1929 February (Box 85, Folder 1121-1130)
    - League of Nations memoranda, 1929 February 15 (Box 86, Folder 1131)
    - Correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1929 March - Nov, 1930 - 1937, (1935) (Box 86, Folder 1132-1137)
  - St. Paul's School, Concord, New Hampshire
    - Annual report of the rector, 1927 (Box 86, Folder 1138)
    - Report of engineering development for St. Paul's School, 1925 October
    - Minutes of board of directors meeting, 1922 January 26
    - Minutes of the meetings of the board of trustees, 1923 January 25, April 26 (Box 86, Folder 1139)
    - List of securities, 1927 August 31
    - Supplementary report on examination of accounts for the year ending Budget reports, 1927. August 31, 1922 - 1923
    - Financial report for the year ending, 1927 August 31 (Box 86, Folder 1140)
  - Washington Cathedral
    - Unemployment organization in parishes (Box 86, Folder 1141)
    - Cathedral lunches invitation lists (Box 86, Folder 1142-1143)
  - Yale-in-China
    - Correspondence, (1915), 1919 May-Nov, 1920 January - June (Box 87, Folder 1144-1147)
    - Correspondence and printed material, 1951 - 1954 (Box 87, Folder 1148)
    - Financial report to the board of trustees Additional financial papers, 1919 November 10-13 (Box 87, Folder 1149)
    - Certificate of incorporation of China Medical Board, Inc.; A visit to Yale-in-China; A report to the board of trustees by Anson Phelps Stokes, 1920 June (Box 87, Folder 1150)
    - Printed material (Box 87, Folder 1151)
    - Fragments and unidentified materials (Box 87, Folder 1152)
    - Yale-in-China
      See: Rachel A. Dowd, Part I, box 18, folder 281 See: Edward H. Hume, Part I, box 25, folder 406 See: Harold Vreeland, Part II, box 43, folder 658 See: Frederick Wells Williams, Part II, box 46 See: Amos P. Wilder, Yale-in-China, Correspondence, Part II, Series III, box 87, folder 1144-1147 See: Brownell Gage, Part II, Series I See: William H. Sallmon, Part II, Series I
- Memorabilia and Photographs, 1896-1954; PART II. IV; 1.5 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Part II, Series IV, Memorabilia and Photographs, consists of unbound scrap-book material compiled by Anson Phelps Stokes, as well as biographical material and photographs of Stokes, friends, and family members.
  The unbound memorabilia appears to have been intended for "Ancestors of Anson Phelps Stokes", which can be found in Series IV of the main portion of the papers. Materials with biographical and or personal significance, such as programs, advertisements and bulletins in which his name was mentioned, may also be found in this section of the addition.
  The two photograph albums and several large photographs too large to be filed with the other items in this series will be found in Box 90.
  - Memorabilia
    - Memorabilia (Box 88, Folder 1153-1157)
    - Memorabilia (Box 88, Folder 1158)
    - "Family Incidents and Memories" by APS
      See: Series II, Section A. Journals and Memoranda
    - Biographical materials (Box 88, Folder 1159)
    - Photographs of APS (Box 88, Folder 1160)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified materials (Box 88, Folder 1161)
    - Additional photographs and photograph albums
      See: Part I, box 90, folder 1457-1459
- Financial and Property Records, 1923-1955 (primarily 1923-1927, 1951-1955); PART II. V
  Part II, Series V, Financial and Property Records, consists of cancelled checks, bank statements, checkbooks and tax records. Additional in-formation concerning family properties can be obtained by checking Series III, Sections E and F.
  NOTE: The Phelps: Stokes Estates later became the Phelps Stokes Corporation.
  - Financial and Property Records
    - Cancelled checks and bank statements, 1923 May - June (Box 88, Folder 1162)
    - Checkbook, 1922 February 9 - 1922 May 20, 1926 October 18 - 1926 December 16, 1926 December 15 - 1927 February 14, 1927 May 10 - 1927 July 19 (Box 88, Folder 1163-1166)
    - Checkbook, 1927 July 19 - 1927 September 26, 1927 October 10 - 1927 December 13 (Box 89, Folder 1167)
    - Taxes, 1905, 1909, 1911, 1914 - 1920, 1922, 1951 - 1955 (Box 89, Folder 1169-1172)
    - Miscellaneous financial and property records (Box 89, Folder 1173)
- Stokes Family Papers, 1900-1921; PART II. VI; .25 lienar feet (1/2 box)
  Part II, Series VI, the Stokes Family Papers, consists of a folder of family correspondence, other than that of Anson Phelps Stokes; a book written by Anson Phelps Stokes (father of APS); and papers, including some correspondence, dealing with the Americana collection of Anson Phelps Stokes (father of APS).
  Additional papers, including ravel memorabilia and Reminiscences of Anson Phelps Stokes, 1874-1954, were received in 1977.
  - Stokes Family Papers
    - Stokes Family correspondence, 1900, 1906, 1913 - 1914, 1920 - 1921 (Box 89, Folder 1174)
    - Cruising in the Ceribbean with a Camera by Anson Phelps Stokes (father of APS), 1903 (Box 89, Folder 1175)
    - Papers relating to the Americana Collection of Anson Phelps Stokes (father of APS) (Box 89, Folder 1176)
    - Two photograph albums of a trip around the world in 1896 and miscellaneous photographs (Box 90, Folder 1177)
    - Miscellaneous photographs and negatives, Canoe trip, 1891 (Box 90, Folder 1178)
    - Roratonga, 1914 (Box 90, Folder 1178)
    - Trip to New Zealand and Australia, 1920 (Box 90, Folder 1178)
    - Photographs from trip around the world, 1897 (Box 90a)
    - Scrapbook — "Illustrating 100 Days in France, with trips to Italy and England during the Great War - Jan 1 to May 1, 1918" Letters home laid in, 1918 January 6 - April 22, 1917 December - 1918 May (Box 91, Folder 1179)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Reminiscences typescript with corrections, pp. 1-68, undated (Box 92, Folder 1180)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Reminiscences typescript with corrections, pp. 69-97a, undated (Box 92, Folder 1181)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Reminiscences typescript with corrections, pp. 98-138, undated (Box 92, Folder 1182)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Reminiscences typescript with corrections, pp. 140-195c, undated (Box 92, Folder 1183)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps, Reminiscences bound volume, 1956 (Box 92, Folder 1184)
- Microfilm Inventory, 1887-1970
  Scrapbooks, 1913-1917, 1919-1924. 23 v.
  Microfilm. New Haven, Yale University Library, 1980. 7 reels.
  Negative available.
  The scrapbooks contain clippings, primarily of political events. Each volume is separately indexed. For additional papers of Harold Phelps Stokes, see Mss 645.
  - 1913 December - 1914 May
  - 1914 May - 1914 November
  - 1914 November - 1915 April
  - 1915 April - 1916 February
  - New York Constitutional Convention of 1915
  - 1916 February - 1916 August
  - 1916 August - 1917 May
  - 1919 January - 1919 March
  - 1919 September - 1919 November
  - 1919 November - 1920 January
  - 1920 January - 1920 April
  - 1920 April - 1920 June
  - 1920 June - 1920 July
  - 1920 July - 1920 August
  - 1920 August - 1920 October
  - 1920 October - 1920 December
  - 1920 December - 1921 January
  - 1921 January - 1921 April
  - 1921 April - 1921 August
  - 1921 September - 1922 March
  - 1923 January - 1923 April
  - 1923 April - 1923 November
  - 1923 November - 1924 April
- Additional material, Accession 1995-M-029
  The accession comprises two reels of films of Anson Phelps Stokes and family. They are originals. Readers may be required to pay for the costs of creating duplicating masters and reproducing use copies for the film they wish to view.
  - Film [Anson Phelps Stokes and family], undated (Box 1)
- Additional material, 1940-1945; Accession 1986-M-099
  This accession consists of correspondence and research materials, chiefly notes and drafts, relating to Anson Phelps Stokes's book, Church and State. Correspondence is between Ellen Ahern, a research archivist at the New York Public Library, and Stokes; some letters are written by Stokes's secretary, Rosalie A. Malone. Ahern answered Stokes's occasional research queries; located and made typed transcripts of many quotations to which he wanted to refer in his text; assisted in preparing footnotes; and typed portions of his manuscript.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research materials, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
- Additional material, undated; Accession 2006-M-020
  - Collection of mounted photographs of the Far East and India
    - Korea, undated (Box 1)
    - China, undated (Box 2)
    - Malay Peninsula, undated (Box 3)
    - India, undated (Box 4–5)
    - Snapshots from various countries in southeast and south Asia, undated (Box 6)